Guide to the James Dowling Trask Papers
Yale University. Department of Manuscripts and Archives
James Dowling Trask papers
1837-1945
MS 1339
Yale University. Department of Manuscripts and Archives
2
(2 boxes)
The papers consist of personal papers, memorabilia, photographs and medals of James Dowling Trask (1890-1942), his father and grandfather (1821-1883), also named James Dowling Trask. The bulk of the collection is related to James Dowling Trask (1890-1942).
Trask, James Dowling, 1890-1942
Immediate Source of Acquisition
Transferred from the Yale University Historical Medical Library, 1980.
Biographical / Historical
James Dowling Trask was born in Astoria, New York on August 21, 1890. After receiving his Ph.B. from Yale College in 1913, Trask went to Cornell Medical College from which he received an M.D. in 1917. Following service in the army and medical research, Trask returned to Yale in 1921 to become an instructor at the School of Medicine. That same year, he married Phyllis Hayden Randall, with whom he would have one daughter, also named Phyllis. Specializing in pediatrics, Trask focused his research on pneumonia, scarlet fever and streptococcal infections. He died in the spring of 1942 of septicemia and peritonitis.
Scope and Contents
The papers consist of personal papers, memorabilia, photographs and medals of James Dowling Trask (1890-1942), his father and grandfather (1821-1883), also named James Dowling Trask. The bulk of the collection is related to James Dowling Trask (1890-1942).
Conditions Governing Access
The materials are open for research.
Arrangement
The papers are arranged by family member.
Medicine; Trask, James Dowling, 1890-1942
- James Dowling Trask (1890-1942)
  - Bellevue Hospital and U.S. Army, 1917-1921 (Box 1, Folder 1)
  - Biographical and family information, Circa 1876-circa 1934 (Box 1, Folder 2)
  - Clippings on polio and Trask's death, Circa 1930s-circa 1940s (Box 1, Folder 3)
  - Cornell University Medical College, correspondence, 1916-1917 (Box 1, Folder 4)
  - Cornell University Medical College, notebooks on bacteriology and clinical laboratory methods (2 notebooks), 1914-1915 (Box 2, Folder 1-2)
  - Correspondence to his father, 1918 (Box 1, Folder 5)
  - Correspondence and conference ephemera, 1934-1942 (Box 1, Folder 6)
  - Correspondence, including with Julia H. Trask (Trask's mother), Circa 1930s-circa 1940s (Box 1, Folder 7)
  - Correspondence, last letters, 1942 May (Box 1, Folder 8)
  - Correspondence relating to Dr. Trask's death, 1942 (Box 1, Folder 9)
  - Discharge from the Army, 1918 (Box 1, Folder 10)
  - Grace-New Haven Community Hospital memorial opportunities booklet, 1951 (Box 1, Folder 11)
  - Great Britain, mostly official correspondence, 1929-1930 (Box 1, Folder 12)
  - Journal, 1941-1942 (Box 1, Folder 13)
  - Juvenalia, sketchbook and reports from Lawrenceville School, 1900-1907 (Box 1, Folder 14-15)
  - Liberty ship James D. Trask, correspondence, photographs, and printed ephemera, 1943-1944 (Box 1, Folder 16)
  - Long Island College of Medicine anniversary, 1940 (Box 1, Folder 17)
  - Memoria and tributes, 1942-1945 (Box 1, Folder 18)
  - Nu Sigma Nu fraternity citation, 1917 (Box 1, Folder 19)
  - Obituaries and resolutions, 1942 (Box 1, Folder 20)
  - Photograph and sketch album, Circa 1890-circa 1910 (Box 1, Folder 21)
  - Photographs of James Dowling Trask, 1895, 1908 (Box 2, Folder 3)
  - Photographs, mostly portraits of James Dowling Trask, 1908-1942 (Box 2, Folder 4)
  - Polio, articles from popular magazines, 1934-1961 (Box 1, Folder 22)
  - Printed ephemera, passports, memberships, and other documents, Circa 1919-1942 (Box 1, Folder 23)
  - Printed ephemera, "The Doctor", Circa 1920 (Box 2, Folder 5)
  - Public health posters, 1940s (Box 1, Folder 24)
  - Research data, 1927 (Box 1, Folder 25)
  - Rockefeller Institute appointment and correspondence, 1919-1920 (Box 1, Folder 26-27)
  - Scarlet Fever by James D. Trask, 1940 (Box 2, Folder 6)
  - Sheffield Scientific School, Yale University, grades and class bulletins, 1909-1939 (Box 1, Folder 28)
  - Tintype, Trask family, 1900 (Box 2, Folder 7)
  - Trask Room, New Haven Hospital, 1942 (Box 1, Folder 29)
  - War and medical decorations and realia, Circa 1917-circa 1942 (Box 2, Folder 8)
  - World War II, War Department correspondence and orders, 1935-1936 (Box 1, Folder 30)
  - Yachting notebook, Circa 1931-circa 1941 (Box 1, Folder 31)
  - Yale Journal of Biology and Medicine, James Dowling Trask Memorial Number (vol. 16, no. 5), 1944 (Box 1, Folder 32)
- James Dowling Trask (Senior)
  - Financial records, correspondence, and printed ephemera relating to his medical practice, Circa 1876-circa 1901 (Box 2, Folder 9)
  - Physicians diary, 1880-1890 (Box 2, Folder 10)
- James Dowling Trask (Senior) and James Dowling Trask (1820-1883), public health and medical practice manuscripts and memorabilia, Circa 1880s-circa 1940s (Box 2, Folder 11)
- James Dowling Trask (1820-1883)
  - Amherst College student notebook, 1837 (Box 2, Folder 12)
  - Public health and medical practice manuscripts and memorabilia, Circa 1860s-circa 1880s (Box 2, Folder 13-14)